NICANOR LEGARTE GUINTO, Ph.D.

Associate Professor I & Director Office of Research Services Southern Luzon State University Lucban, Quezon Philippines

Permanent Address:

95 San Pedro St., La Milagrosa Subd., Brgy. 9, Lucena City, Quezon, Philippines

+639953888027 Contact No:

Email: (work) nguinto@slsu.edu.ph

Academic Information:

http://www.slsucas.net/faculty/dllh/nicanorguinto



Short bionote

Nicanor Guinto is an Associate Professor and Director of the Office Research Services at Southern Luzon State University. He holds a PhD in Language, Discourse, and Communication from the joint academic program of the University of Hong Kong & King's College London, University of London. He has given research talks and has international publications on areas such as language and transnational labor migration, linguistic ethnography, geosemiotics, critical pedagogy, and media discourse.

Education

Joint PhD in Sociolinguistics/ Language, Discourse & Communication (2016-2021) Jointly offered by The University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong SAR (Home Institution) and King's College London, University of London, United Kingdom (Partner Institution) Supervisors: Prof. Adam Jaworski (HKU) & Prof. Ben Rampton (KCL) Postgraduate Scholar of the University of Hong Kong & CHED Partial Support for Foreign Studies Scholar (Philippines)

Co- and extra- curricular Responsibilities:

- Steering Committee, Cross-London Sociolinguistics Seminar (KCL, AY 2018-2019)
- Course Tutor, ENGL2141: Doing discourse analysis (HKU, Semester 1, AY 2017-2018)
- Co-Editor of the HKU School of English Alumni Magazine (2017-2018)
- Editor & Writer, Newsletter of the HKU Graduate House (June 2017 Issue)
- HKU Student Representative, Talks on Postgraduate Opportunities at the University of HK in Manila (September 13-15, 2017)
- Conference Organizer, HKU Postgraduate Conference in Sociolinguistics: Multimodal and Mediated Discourse analysis (Conference held on September 28-29, 2017)

Master of Arts in English Studies: Language (2011-2015)

University of the Philippines-Diliman (CHED Center of Excellence in English Language)

Quezon City, Philippines

Awards Received: University Scholar

Bachelor of Secondary Education Major in English - Cum Laude (2005-2009)

Southern Luzon State University, Lucban, Quezon, Philippines Awards Received: Outstanding Pre-Service Teacher in English, Gov. Rafael P. Nantes Award of Academic Excellence

Work Experience

OIC-Director of SLSU Office of Research Services (March 1, 2022-present)

Department Head [Designation] (September 4, 2021 – February 28, 2022)

Associate Professor 1 (July 1, 2019 - present)

Assistant Professor 1 (June 16, 2017 – June 30, 2019)

Instructor III (May, 2015 - June 15, 2017)

College Research Coordinator [Designation] (June 29, 2015 – July 29, 2016)

Contractual Instructor (January, 2015 - April, 2015)

Contract of Service Instructor (June, 2009 – December, 2014)

Department of Languages, Literature and Humanities

College of Arts and Sciences

Southern Luzon State University

Lucban, Quezon, Philippines

Instructor (June 2010-October, 2010)

Interglobal College Foundation

Lucena City

Other Work-related Experiences

- Peer Reviewer
 - o International Journal on the Sociology of Language
 - o Diliman Review
 - Philippine Humanities Review
 - o Plaridel: A Philippine Journal of Communication, Media, & Society
 - o Social Transformations: Journal of the Global South
 - o The Journal of Language Teaching & Learning
 - o Asian Journal of English Language Studies
- Editorial Consultant & Peer Reviewer, TILAMSIK: The Southern Luzon Journal of Arts and Sciences (Vol. 9, Issues 1 & 2, Sept. 2016 & March 2017 Issues)
- College of Arts and Sciences Research Coordinator (August 2015 July 2016)
- Website Administrator, SLSU CAS Official Website
- Editor-in-Chief, TILAMSIK: The Southern Luzon Journal of Arts and Sciences (Vol. 8, Issue 2, Mar. 2016)
- Issue Editor, TILAMSIK: The Southern Luzon Journal of Arts and Sciences (Vol. 8, Issue 1, July 2015)
- Writer, The Core: The Official Newsletter of the SLSU AACCUP Accreditation (2009 present)

Special Prizes/ Awards

Emerging Scholar, Linguistic Landscapes Workshop 10 & University of Bern, Bern, Switzerland, May 2-4, 2018

Best Research Presenter, HKU Postgraduate Conference in Sociolinguistics: Multi-modal and Mediated Discourse Analysis, The University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong, China, September 28-29, 2017

Outstanding Faculty for 2016, Program for Awards and Service Incentives-Southern Luzon State University, March 17, 2017

Exemplary Behavior Award (for Teaching Personnel), Program for Awards and Service Incentives-Southern Luzon State University, March 17, 2015

Finalist, Why Youth Blogging Competition, Asian Development Bank & Plan India, April 9, 2013

University Scholar, University of the Philippines Diliman, February, 2013

Selected Publications

- Aguilo, C., Guinto, N., Aberion, L. (2022). Chapter 16: Discourse Analysis. In Rosario, A. & Wa-Mbeleke, S. (Eds.), The SAGE Handbook of Qualitative Research in the Asian Context. London: Sage.
- Guinto, N. L., Villaverde, B. D., & Manzanilla, S. M. (2021). (Un)thinking the "new" in the new normal: Reflections on ways forward from the Southern Luzon State University. In F. dlC Paragas (Ed.), Higher Education Interventions During and Beyond the COVID-19 Pandemic (pp. 57–64). Quezon City, Philippines: University of the Philippines Center for Integrative and Development Studies.
- Guinto, N.L. (2019). The place/s of Tagalog in Hong Kong's Central district: Negotiating center-periphery dynamics. Linguistic Landscape: An International Journal, 5(2). 160-178. DOI: 10.1075/II.18024.gui
- Guinto, N. L.. (2016). Composition Errors of Second Year Engineering Students of SLSU: **Description and Pedagogical Implications**. *Tilamsik: The Southern Luzon Journal of Arts* and Sciences, 8(2). 59-70.
- Guinto, N. L. (2015b). Approaching Cultural Differences in the Assessment of Students' English Compositions. MINSCAT, EDS Business School and TUCST Research Journal 2(2).
- Guinto, N. L. (2015a). Defying Orthodoxy: A Critique on the Distinctive Features Theory of Trubetzkov, Jakobson and Chomsky. Tilamsik: The Southern Luzon Journal of Arts and Sciences 8(1). 204-208.
- Guinto, N.L. (2014b). Categorical Analysis of Post-Graduate Research on English Studies in selected Universities and Colleges in Southern Luzon (2001-2011). Siyasig Special Golden Issue.
- Guinto, N. L. (2014a). Segmental features of English modeled by selected professors in a state university in the Philippines: Implications in teaching English. International Journal of Research Studies in Language Learning 3(1), 67-80, DOI: 10.5861/ijrsll.2013.475

- Guinto, N. L. (2013). <u>Ideological constructions in column titles by two age groups in the Philippines: Implications in language teaching and learning</u>. *International Journal of Research Studies in Language Learning* 2(5). 105-116. DOI: 10.5861/ijrsll.2013.372
- Guinto, N. L. (2012b). <u>Defying Rhetorical Orthodox: The Filipino Youth and the Structure of their Narrative Essays</u>. *Refereed Proceedings of the Annual Conference on Journalism and Mass Communications* held at Hotel Fort Canning, Singapore on December 4-7, 2012. DOI: 10.5176/2301-3729_JMComm12.54

Books

- Manzanilla, S.M., Dizon, J.M., & **Guinto**, **N.L.** [Eds.] (2016). *Communication in the scientific and technical professions*. Lucban, Philippines: SLSU Department of Languages, Literature, and Humanities. ISBN 978-621-95386-3-3
- **Guinto, N.L.** & Villaverde, B.D. (2015). Functional English in a global society 2: Developing study and thinking skills in English. Lucban, Philippines: SLSU Department of Languages, Literature, and Humanities. ISBN 978-621-95386-4-0
- Manzanilla, S.M. & **Guinto, N.L.** [Eds.] (2015). Writing in the professions: Technical report writing. Lucban, Philippines: SLSU Department of Languages, Literature, and Humanities. ISBN 978-621-95386-2-6
- **Guinto, N.L.** & Villaverde, B.D. (2011) *Functional English in a global society: Vocabulary building and communicative grammar*. Lucban, Philippines: SLSU Department of Languages, Literature, and Humanities. ISBN 978-621-95386-1-9

Invited Plenary/Keynote Research Presentation

Home-making in Sunday-Central: Structures of feeling among Filipino migrant domestic workers in Hong Kong

Part of the Plenary Themed Panel for the 2022 Joint Linguistic Society of the Philippines International Conference & English in Southeast Asia International Conference Organized by: Linguistic Society of the Philippines March 10-12, 2022

Decolonizing English Language Teaching and Learning: Educators' Voices

Organized by: Ateneo Center for English Language Teaching & The Sociolinguist Inquirer October 15, 2021

Introduction to Qualitative Data Analysis

Presented during the 1st DepEd Division of Davao City Senior High School Summit July 6-9, 2021

Home-making in Sunday-Central: Structures of feeling among Filipino migrant domestic workers in Hong Kong

Presented at the King's College London Language, Discourse and Communication Doctoral Lab

Linguistic Ethnography: What it is and how we may do it

Presented at the Mindanao State University-Main Campus, Marawi City, "Webinar Series on Language Research"

May 31, 2021

Doing Discourse Analysis

Presented at the Asian Qualitative Research Association Webinar November 12, 2020

Chronotopic (re)configuration in life stories of Filipino domestic workers in Hong Kong

To be presented at Young Scholars Forum at the 2020 International Conference on Applied Linguistics and Language Education (ICALLE), De La Salle University, Manila February 27-29, 2020

Semiotic landscape in the periphery: Examining the discursive infrastructure of transnational labor migration in Hong Kong (with Emerging Scholars Grant from **XSCAPES** and UniBe)

Presented at the XSCAPES: Linguistic Landscapes Workshop 10, University of Bern, Switzerland May 2-4, 2018

Mobility in the Margins: Linguistic Repertoire of a Filipina Domestic Worker in Hong

Global South Perspectives: An International Workshop Hong Kong Baptist University, Hong Kong April 20, 2017

Selected Research Paper Presentations

Value(ation) of being "ma-kwento" (chatty) in English: Examining the metalinguistic narratives of a Filipina domestic worker in Hong Kong

Presented during e-Sociolinguistics Symposium at the University of Hong Kong June 7-10, 2021

The Places of Tagalog in Hong Kong's Central District

Presented at the Filipino Postgraduate Forum, Philippine Embassy in the United Kingdom, London,

July 27, 2019

Semiotic landscape in the periphery: Examining the discursive infrastructure of transnational labor migration in Hong Kong

Presented at the Sociolinguistics Symposium 22, University of Auckland, New Zealand June 26-29, 2018

Tracing mobilities in the margins: The linguistic portrait of a Filipina domestic worker in **Hong Kong**

Presented at the ECS Doctoral Conference 2018, King's College, University of London, United Kingdom May 19, 2018

Semiotic landscape in the periphery: Examining the discursive infrastructure of transnational labor migration in Hong Kong (Best Research Presenter)

HKU Postgraduate Conference in Sociolinguistics: Multi-modal and Mediated Discourse

The University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong, China September 28-29, 2017

Preliminaries to the Sociolinguistics of Decentered Mobility (with HKU Pilot Scheme for **Internationalisation for RPG Grant)**

Copenhagen PhD Winter School in Sociolinguistics University of Copenhagen, Copenhagen, Denmark March 13-17, 2017

Writing Assessment in the Philippines: Challenges and Implications in the ASEAN Integration

5th Center for Language Communication International Symposium Organized by: National University of Singapore - Centre for Language Communication Venue: Stephen Riady Centre, National University of Singapore, Singapore Date: May 25-27, 2016

Approaching Cultural Differences in the Assessment of Students' English Compositions

2nd MINSCAT, EDS, & THU International Research Seminar & Presentations Organized by: Mindoro State College of Agriculture & Technology, Philippines, EDS Academy, Malaysia & That Hua University, Vietnam Venue: Tamaraw Hotel & Resort, Puerto Galera, Oriental Mindoro, Philippines

Date: October 5-6, 2015

Negotiation of (Non)Academic Identity in, and the Transgressive Linguistic Landscape of, University Library Textbook Marginalia

9th International Free Linguistics Conference *Organized by:* the Linguistics Society of the Philippines

Venue: De La Salle University, Manila

Date: September 24-26, 2015

"Puta! Masyadong technical ang gago!": Negotiation of (Non)Academic Identity in, and the Transgressive Linguistic Landscape of, University Library Textbook Marginalia

12th Philippine Linguistics Congress

Organized by: UP-Diliman Department of Linguistics

Venue: University of the Philippines-Diliman, Quezon City

Date: November 26-28, 2014

Creative & Other Publications

"The Philippines I want to inherit"

Young Blood column: Opinion Page Philippine Daily Inquirer, November 7, 2016 http://opinion.inquirer.net/98990/philippines-want-inherit

"Plagiarism" (Republished as a book chapter)

Youngblood 5: Best Essays published in the Philippine Daily Inquirer from 2012 to 2013 Edited by: Ruel S. De Vera, Rosario A. Garcellano, Pam Pastor, Javier Vicente D. Rufino

Published by: Inquirer Books (2015)

ISBN: 978-971-8935-25-5

"Plagiarism"

"Young Blood" Column: Opinion Page Philippine Daily Inquirer, October 9, 2012 http://opinion.inquirer.net/byline/nicanor-l-guinto

How to teach English

Inquirer Learning
Philippine Daily Inquirer, February 27, 2012
http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/152253/how-to-teach-english

Seminars and Trainings

Gearing up for the Next Normal: Training of Teachers on the Flexible Learning Mode

University of the Philippines Open University July 1-August 10, 2021

Copenhagen PhD Winter School in Sociolinguistics

University of Copenhagen, Copenhagen, Denmark March 13-17, 2017

Trainers' Training on Translating Research Results into ISI-Publishable Format

Organizer: Philippine Council for Agriculture, Aquatic, and Natural Resources Research and

Development

Date: November 3-7, 2015

Venue: AIM Conference Center, Baguio City, Philippines

Language Research Design, Implementation, and Report Writing

Organizer: International English Language Teaching Institute

Date: November 16-18, 2013

Venue: Hotel Supreme, Baguio City, Philippines

IT Course Design and Development

Organizer: National Computer Center

Date: April 16 - May 13, 2013

Venue: National Computer Center, Diliman, Quezon City, Philippines

Advanced English Proficiency Training

Organizer: Business Processing Association of the Philippines & the Provincial Government

of Quezon Province *Date*: May 21-30, 2012

Venue: Quezon Science High School, Lucena City, Philippines

Volunteer Work, Community & Expert Service

Co-organizer

1st Winter School on Migration Linguistics Tokyo University of Foreign Studies, Tokyo, Japan February 9-11, 2022

Consultant

Research conducted by Dr. Jess Datu of the Education University of Hong Kong October-December, 2021

Ambassador, Domestic Worker Empowerment Project

The University of Hong Kong

I put up, maintain, and write for the organization website (http://www.dwep.org)

Iournalism Consultant

Department of Education, District of Sariaya

Conducts trainings and workshops to High School students on Journalistic and technical writing

SLSU-based Projects

1. Preliminary Study on the Information Technology - Business Process Outsourcing (IT-BPM) in Region IV-A CALABARZON [COMPLETED, 2017]

A research in collaboration with the College of Business Administration, funded by the DOST and SLSU amounting to Php 816, 400.00 (US\$ 16800). I serve as researcher and writer. Project Duration: June 2016-December 2016

2. Documentation of Indigenous Peoples in Region IV-A CALABARZON [COMPLETED, 2020]

A research/ coffee table book project with funding from Senator Loren Legarda amounting to Php 2 Million (US \$ 43, 000). I serve as researcher and lead writer.

3. Errors in Senior High School students' essays: Groundwork for instructional design in Purposive Communication [COMPLETED: March, 2021]

This study sought to enhance the instructional design of Purposive Communication guided by the identified mechanical, morpho-syntactic and discourse errors in compositions/essays of selected high school students in Quezon Province.

Organizational Membership

- 1. International Adviser, Migration Linguistics Unit-Tokyo University of Foreign Studies
- 2. Member, Asian Qualitative Research Association
- 3. Member, Linguistic Society of the Philippines

Certifications

Certificate of Teaching and Learning in Higher Education

Conferred by the University of Hong Kong, Centre for the Enhancement of Teaching and Learning, January 3, 2017

Licensed Professional Teacher (License No. 1046305)

Conferred by the Professional Regulation Commission (PRC), Philippines

Advanced English Proficiency Trainer (Grammar and Fluency)

Conferred by the Business Process Outsourcing Association of the Philippines

Civil Service Eligible

PD (Honor Graduate)

I hereby testify that the above information is true and correct as of March 30, 2022.

NICANOR I. GUINTO